<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Gigi Sung&#39;s Workspace</title>
<link>https://gigisung0503.github.io/Doodling/</link>
<atom:link href="https://gigisung0503.github.io/Doodling/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Doodling and brief book-keeping of a day</description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.551</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 22:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Review: Take This Waltz, 2011</title>
  <dc:creator>Gigi Sung</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gigisung0503.github.io/Doodling/posts/2025-01-07-Movie.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>Take This Waltz: Restlessness in Comfortable Love</strong></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2022/05/25/arts/take-anatomy1/take-anatomy1-superJumbo.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Michelle Williams in Take This Waltz (My favorite scene) Credit: https://www.nytimes.com/2012/06/29/movies/take-this-waltz-directed-by-sarah-polley.html</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Sarah Polley’s second feature film, <em>Take This Waltz</em>, dives into the uneasy space between affection, routine, and longing. Whereas her debut, <em>Away From Her</em>, told the story of an older couple facing Alzheimer’s, <em>Take This Waltz</em> focuses on a younger marriage quietly slipping into dissatisfaction. The result is a candid look at how even a seemingly happy relationship can push someone to crave something thrilling and new.</p>
<hr>
<section id="a-marriage-of-familiar-routines" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-marriage-of-familiar-routines">A Marriage of Familiar Routines</h3>
<p>Margot (Michelle Williams) and Lou (Seth Rogen) appear to have a pleasant, easygoing life. He’s a cookbook writer immersed in developing chicken recipes; she’s bright and imaginative. Their shared comfort suggests they’re doing just fine—until Margot meets Daniel (Luke Kirby). His spontaneity electrifies something in her that routine and security just can’t touch.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="symbolic-hints-chicken-and-the-scrambler" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="symbolic-hints-chicken-and-the-scrambler">Symbolic Hints: Chicken and the Scrambler</h3>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://newcityfilm.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/coupledetat4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>A Fairground Scrambler Ride —An Exhilarating Blur of Lights, Speed, and Chaos Credit: https://newcityfilm.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/coupledetat4.jpg</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Polley uses quiet symbols to capture Margot’s state of mind. Lou’s endless chicken experiments point to his sincere yet predictable approach to life—steadfast but lacking surprise. Meanwhile, the Scrambler ride at a fairground stands in for Margot’s chaotic, head-spinning attraction to Daniel. As fun as it looks, it’s easy to end up dizzy and disoriented, unsure whether the rush truly solves anything or just repeats a familiar pattern with a new face.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="shifts-in-perspective" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="shifts-in-perspective">Shifts in Perspective</h3>
<p>Visually, Polley keeps us on our toes. Scenes that first appear to show Margot cooking for Lou might suddenly reveal she’s with Daniel instead, underlining how blurred the line can be between devotion and transgression. In one montage set to Leonard Cohen’s “Take This Waltz,” <strong>we watch Margot and Daniel’s relationship unfold in a rush—from its magnetic start to its sobering shift back into routine.</strong></p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="a-troubling-question" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-troubling-question">A Troubling Question</h3>
<p><strong>The core dilemma:</strong> <em style="color: #355C7D;">Is Margot’s restlessness about her marriage or about her own inability to settle down?</em> Lou is not cruel or neglectful—he’s genuinely caring, even a bit playful. Yet his unwavering stability may be part of what makes Margot itch to break free. Polley never labels Margot’s desire as “wrong” or “right.” Instead, she shows how people can drift away from good partners, lured by the promise of excitement—only to wonder if they’ll end up right where they started.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="why-it-resonates" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-it-resonates">Why It Resonates</h3>
<p>Ultimately, <em>Take This Waltz</em> shows how love can toggle between the comfort of the known and the spark of the unfamiliar. By the film’s end, there’s no tidy answer—only a reminder that longing can stem as much from within ourselves as it can from our circumstances. Polley leaves us reflecting on whether a new relationship is ever truly new, or if we keep recreating the same patterns in a different guise. It’s a thoughtful, lingering portrait of how the search for happiness might just circle back to the restlessness that sent us searching in the first place.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="a-personal-reflection" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-personal-reflection">A Personal Reflection</h3>
<p>This film was a source of deep comfort for me. It also set me free from a lingering sense of guilt that had been weighing on me until quite recently. In my own past relationship, I was essentially in Lou’s position. From Margot’s perspective (or the director’s lens following Margot), Lou is portrayed as someone who values stability—almost to the point of seeming flat. I suspect that was a conscious choice in the film, a kind of cinematic compromise to underscore the contrast between Lou and Daniel.</p>
<p>Yet in my mind, Lou might be a far more sensitive soul than the film lets on. He could be the type who finds a sense of novelty in every small shift—whether it’s cooking chicken yet again or uttering the same “I love you” that others might find stale. Maybe those “boring” daily acts of affection felt fresh to Lou in subtle ways. Who knows? At least, that was my case.</p>
<p>Margot, however, seems to be tuned to a different frequency. To her, life with Lou feels like a cycle stuck on repeat, with no variation. Once Margot decides their marriage is “boring,” Lou’s every quality becomes monochromatic to her, as if she’s slipped a gray filter ovemr him. Interestingly, Daniel—Margot’s supposed alternative—turns out not to be the ideal she imagined. That part, oddly enough, gave me some solace.</p>
<p>I never truly learned why my own relationship had to end, though I suspect “boredom” was a major factor, and I ended up blaming myself for causing it. Seeing Margot’s endless restlessness hinted at in the film was a comfort. Realizing that someone like Margot—driven by impulses no one can fully quell—would struggle to find lasting contentment made me feel liberated. I may sound a bit twisted saying so.</p>
<p>That being said, I’d like to discuss moral (or could be ehtical) considerations w relationships in my next post. Will share more soon.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>review</category>
  <guid>https://gigisung0503.github.io/Doodling/posts/2025-01-07-Movie.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Random Thoughts in These Days</title>
  <dc:creator>Gigi Sung</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gigisung0503.github.io/Doodling/posts/2025-01-05.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>These days, I have been working and concentrating on spending quality alone time. I have been learning a lot, but I have not been able to write down my thoughts. Not because I haven’t had time to do so, but because I was sure that I would not commit myself to putting enough time and effort into fully capturing my emotions and thoughts. This is what I feel whenever I keep a journal. After some time, when I revisit the pieces, I am surprised by how flat and reduced the texts are, and I soon become deflated by the fact that the mediocre words have overwritten my rich feelings and thoughts. But regardless of the fact that my writing almost always fails to capture the sophisticated aspects of my thoughts, I still feel the need to write.</p>
<p>Or else, the only artifacts that I leave on Earth would be those of ChatGPT. I admit that the text prediction model is quite impressive, and most of the time, generates more concise and quintessential pieces. The texts are almost too perfect, meaning coherent and decisive, that they sound eerie. I wonder if “Uncanny Valley” is not only for visual representation but also for textual representation.</p>
<p>Anyhow, I plan to build muscles for writing. The muscles for reflection and spirituality. The muscles for keeping a record of all the bad and good things happening in my life. About things that drag me down and boost me up. About people who have shared love and people who have manipulated me.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>journal</category>
  <guid>https://gigisung0503.github.io/Doodling/posts/2025-01-05.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Open-source Alternatives to ArcGIS for Web Mapping</title>
  <dc:creator>Gigi Sung</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gigisung0503.github.io/Doodling/posts/2025-01-08-Map.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>When looking for open-source alternatives to Esri’s <code>ArcGIS</code> for serving web-based map applications, you’ll find a vibrant ecosystem of tools and frameworks. <strong><em>Some of these can fully replace <code>ArcGIS</code> in both data handling (server-side) and visualization (client-side)</em></strong>, while others focus on a specific slice of the mapping stack. Below is an overview of key open-source components commonly used to build a complete web mapping solution—from server to client.</p>
<hr>
<section id="client-side-libraries" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="client-side-libraries">1. Client-Side Libraries</h2>
<section id="leaflet" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="leaflet"><strong><code>Leaflet</code></strong></h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>What It Is</strong>: A lightweight JavaScript library for interactive maps.</li>
<li><strong>Why It’s Great</strong>: Easy to learn, large plugin ecosystem, works well with raster tiles (e.g., from <code>Mapbox</code>, <code>OpenStreetMap</code>, or your own tile server).</li>
<li><strong>Typical Use Case</strong>: Quick prototypes or production apps that need simple, slippy maps with markers, pop-ups, and basic overlays.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="openlayers" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="openlayers"><strong><code>OpenLayers</code></strong></h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>What It Is</strong>: A more feature-rich JavaScript library for building advanced web maps.</li>
<li><strong>Why It’s Great</strong>: Offers broad support for geospatial formats (WMS, WMTS, vector tiles, etc.) and more complex GIS-like functionality out-of-the-box.</li>
<li><strong>Typical Use Case</strong>: Applications that need advanced map interactions, projections, and layers without heavy server-side customization.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="maplibre-gl" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="maplibre-gl"><strong><code>MapLibre GL</code></strong></h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>What It Is</strong>: An open-source fork of <code>Mapbox</code> GL JS (licensed under BSD). It provides client-side vector rendering in the browser.</li>
<li><strong>Why It’s Great</strong>: Retains the powerful style specification and performance of <code>Mapbox</code> GL, but free from the proprietary license constraints.</li>
<li><strong>Typical Use Case</strong>: Building highly interactive and customizable vector tile-based web apps with 3D capabilities and smooth zoom/rotation.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
</section>
</section>
<section id="server-side-and-data-hosting" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="server-side-and-data-hosting">2. Server-Side and Data Hosting</h2>
<section id="geoserver" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="geoserver"><strong><code>GeoServer</code></strong></h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>What It Is</strong>: A Java-based server that publishes geospatial data using open standards like WMS, WMTS, WFS, and WCS.</li>
<li><strong>Why It’s Great</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Strong integration with <code>PostGIS</code> (PostgreSQL with geospatial extensions).<br>
</li>
<li>Flexible styling using SLD (Styled Layer Descriptor) or CSS-like styling.<br>
</li>
<li>Large community support, stable, and actively maintained.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Typical Use Case</strong>: Serving vector/raster layers to web apps, enabling OGC-compliant services, or powering complex geospatial workflows.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="mapserver" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mapserver"><strong><code>MapServer</code></strong></h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>What It Is</strong>: One of the oldest and most robust open-source map servers, written in C.</li>
<li><strong>Why It’s Great</strong>:
<ul>
<li>High performance in rendering cartographic maps.<br>
</li>
<li>Also supports OGC standards (WMS, WFS, WCS).<br>
</li>
<li>Lightweight and can be very fast if configured properly.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Typical Use Case</strong>: Projects that need a stable and efficient map server for large datasets or high-traffic scenarios.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="qgis-server" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="qgis-server"><strong><code>QGIS</code> Server</strong></h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>What It Is</strong>: The server component of the <code>QGIS</code> project (an open-source desktop GIS).<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Why It’s Great</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Uses <code>QGIS</code>’s own rendering engine, meaning the same styling you create in <code>QGIS</code> Desktop can be served to the web.<br>
</li>
<li>Supports OGC standards (WMS, WFS).<br>
</li>
<li>Seamless integration with <code>QGIS</code> Desktop, making it convenient to publish layers directly.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Typical Use Case</strong>: Organizations already using <code>QGIS</code> Desktop who want an easier path to publish maps with the same styling online.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
</section>
</section>
<section id="databases-and-data-management" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="databases-and-data-management">3. Databases and Data Management</h2>
<section id="postgis" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="postgis"><strong><code>PostGIS</code></strong></h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>What It Is</strong>: A spatial extension of PostgreSQL, turning it into a powerful geospatial database.</li>
<li><strong>Why It’s Great</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Can store and query large amounts of geospatial data efficiently.<br>
</li>
<li>Supports advanced GIS functions (buffer, intersect, spatial joins) for server-side analysis.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Typical Use Case</strong>: Any open-source web GIS stack that needs robust data storage and on-the-fly spatial querying.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="tileserver-gl-optional-for-vector-tiles" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tileserver-gl-optional-for-vector-tiles"><strong>TileServer GL</strong> (Optional for Vector Tiles)</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>What It Is</strong>: An open-source Node.js server that hosts vector tiles (MBTiles or raw data) and serves them via styles compatible with <code>Mapbox</code>/MapLibre.</li>
<li><strong>Why It’s Great</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Easy to set up a self-hosted vector tile service.<br>
</li>
<li>Works nicely with <code>MapLibre GL</code> or <code>Mapbox</code> GL JS front-ends.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Typical Use Case</strong>: When you want full control over your vector tiles or an offline map environment.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
</section>
</section>
<section id="data-sources-and-basemaps" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-sources-and-basemaps">4. Data Sources and Basemaps</h2>
<p>While you can use your own data, you might also need base layers or geocoding/routing services. Many open-source projects rely on <strong><code>OpenStreetMap</code></strong> data, which is crowdsourced and free. You can either:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Self-host</strong> your own OSM-based tiles with tools like <strong>OpenMapTiles</strong> or <strong>TileServer GL</strong>, or<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Use a third-party service</strong> (e.g., MapTiler, Carto, or <code>Mapbox</code>—though <code>Mapbox</code> is free up to certain usage limits but not fully open-source).</li>
</ul>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="putting-it-all-together" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="putting-it-all-together">5. Putting It All Together</h2>
<p>A typical fully open-source web GIS “stack” might look like this:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Data Storage</strong>: <code>PostGIS</code> (for vector data), GeoTIFFs or other rasters on disk.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Map Server</strong>: <code>GeoServer</code> or <code>MapServer</code> to publish data via WMS/WMTS (raster layers) or WFS (vector data).<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Frontend</strong>: <code>Leaflet</code>, <code>OpenLayers</code>, or <code>MapLibre GL</code> to render maps in the browser and provide interactive features.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Styling and Tiles</strong>: Optionally use TileServer GL or <code>QGIS</code> Server for vector/raster tile services with custom cartography.</li>
</ol>
<p>This setup can replicate much of <code>ArcGIS</code>’s map serving functionality without the licensing costs. You do, however, shoulder more responsibility for setup, security, scalability, and maintenance.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="how-do-these-tools-compare-to-arcgis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-these-tools-compare-to-arcgis">6. How Do These Tools Compare to <code>ArcGIS</code>?</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Cost</strong>:
<ul>
<li><strong>Open-source</strong> solutions are generally free to use (though you may pay for hosting and developer time).<br>
</li>
<li><strong><code>ArcGIS</code></strong> typically requires license fees, which can be significant for large deployments.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Flexibility</strong>:
<ul>
<li><strong>Open-source</strong> stacks let you customize every layer of the system—ideal if you have specific or niche requirements.<br>
</li>
<li><strong><code>ArcGIS</code></strong> provides a well-integrated ecosystem of desktop, online, and enterprise tools, but can be less flexible outside Esri’s ecosystem.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Community &amp; Support</strong>:
<ul>
<li><strong>Open-source</strong> communities (<code>GeoServer</code>, <code>MapServer</code>, <code>QGIS</code>, <code>Leaflet</code>, etc.) are large and active. Premium support can come from third-party consultants or in-house experts.<br>
</li>
<li><strong><code>ArcGIS</code></strong> offers official Esri support, training, and extensive documentation, which some organizations prefer for mission-critical deployments.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Advanced GIS Functions</strong>:
<ul>
<li><strong><code>ArcGIS</code></strong> has built-in advanced tools (e.g., network analysis, 3D, big data analytics) that can be convenient.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Open-source</strong> solutions often require combining multiple tools (e.g., GRASS GIS, <code>PostGIS</code>, Python libraries) to achieve the same functionality. This modularity is powerful but adds complexity.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="including-mapbox-in-the-conversation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="including-mapbox-in-the-conversation">7. Including <code>Mapbox</code> in the Conversation</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong><code>Mapbox</code></strong> itself is not fully open-source (the <code>Mapbox</code> platform is commercial), but many of its underlying components—like [<code>Mapbox</code> GL JS v1 (BSD-licensed up to a certain version)] and <a href="https://github.com/%60mapbox%60/tile-reduce">TileReduce</a>—were open-source or open-core.<br>
</li>
<li><strong><code>MapLibre GL</code></strong> has emerged as a fully open-source alternative that continues the vector rendering engine in a community-led fashion.</li>
</ul>
<p>If you’re comfortable mixing open-source with commercial APIs, <code>Mapbox</code> can be an excellent choice for basemaps, geocoding, and styling—especially if you’re not subject to strict open-source mandates. Otherwise, <code>MapLibre GL</code> plus self-hosted tile services (via TileServer GL or <code>GeoServer</code>) can fulfill a truly open-source pipeline.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2>
<p>Building an open-source web GIS stack requires piecing together various components for data storage (<code>PostGIS</code>), map serving (<code>GeoServer</code>, <code>MapServer</code>, <code>QGIS</code> Server), and frontend visualization (<code>Leaflet</code>, <code>OpenLayers</code>, or <code>MapLibre GL</code>). While <code>ArcGIS</code> offers a one-stop, proprietary solution, open-source alternatives can be just as robust, infinitely flexible, and cost-effective—provided you have the technical expertise (or are willing to learn) to configure and maintain them.</p>
<p>In short, if you’re looking to replace <code>ArcGIS</code> for web-serving map applications with purely open-source tools (including MapLibre/<code>Mapbox</code>-like clients), you’ll find a rich, supportive community and a powerful suite of technologies ready to be tailored to your specific project needs.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>development</category>
  <category>mapping</category>
  <guid>https://gigisung0503.github.io/Doodling/posts/2025-01-08-Map.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
